Finding Aid for the War of 1812 Papers, 1810-1953 (bulk 1812-1875)
Buffalo History Museum. Research Library
War of 1812 Papers, 1810-1953 (bulk 1812-1875)
Mss. B00-15
Buffalo History Museum. Research Library
2 boxes (1 linear foot)
Papers pertaining to the War of 1812.
Administrative Information
Terms of Access
The War of 1812 Papers are open for research.
Administrative Information
Acquisition Information
The manuscripts in this collection were acquired or received by the Buffalo History Museum from many sources between 1865 and 1953. Provenance information for most items has been lost, but whenever possible, items of like provenance have been kept together. The series groupings outlined below reflect subjects or types of documents.
Accruals and Additions
No further accruals are expected to this collection.
Historical Note
Located close to the U.S./Canadian border, Buffalo's role in the War of 1812 is historically significant to the Western New York area.
Scope and Content Note
General orders, proclamations, newspaper reports and letters concerning military campaigns, including papers of Maj. John G. Camp; letterbook of Sir Phineas Riall, 1813-1814; minutes and subscription lists, 1814, of the Committee of Safety and Relief at Canandaigua, and other documents of property losses on the Niagara Frontier; rough draft of a treaty arranging for indemnification for slaves and property seized by British forces, 1822; military commissions and papers related to bounty and pension claims of soldiers and their descendants, 1810-1934; an account of Buffalo's role in the War of 1812 by Laila F. Culbertson, 1899; and ms. catalogs, bibliographies, and an inventory of the A. Conger Goodyear War of 1812 collection.
Arrangement
Organized into four series:
I. Military Campaigns and Treaties, 1812-1925
II. Losses, Claims and Payments to Niagara Frontier War Victims, 1813-1842
III. Commission, Bounty and Pension Papers, 1810-1934
IV. Reminiscences, Catalogs and Bibliographies, 1899-circa 1953.
Chronological arrangement within series.
Container List
- Military Campaigns and Treaties, 1812-1925, I.
  Arranged chronologically.
  - Military activities, 1812-1925, undated (Box-folder 1.1)
    (Includes letters, lists of provisions, commissions, newspaper articles, and reminiscences on various campaigns in the war)
  - Letters of Sir Phineas Riall, copied by his secretary, 1813-1814, (Bound volume) (Box-folder 1.2)
  - General orders, proclamations, and letters, 1813-1835, undated (Box-folder 1.3)
  - Major John G. Camp papers (including papers of Jonathan Davis, Robert Haven, Daniel Stanton and Nathan Stoddard), 1811-1912 (Box-folder 1.4)
  - Rough draft of treaty arranging for indemnification for slaves and private property stolen by British forces, agreed to by Henry Middleton (Minister Plenipotentiary to Russia) and Sir C. Bagot (British Ambassador to Russia), 1 June 1822 (Box-folder 1.6)
- Losses, Claims and Payments to Niagara Frontier War Victims, 1813-1842, II.
  - War losses, claims and payments (including papers of the Committee of Safety and Relief at Canandaigua), 1814-1842 (Box-folder 1.6)
  - Itemized lists of losses of Niagara Frontier war victims, undated, (typed transcripts of originals) (Box-folder 1.7)
  - Committee of Safety and Relief at Canandaigua: contribution and subscription lists, 1814 (Box-folder 1.8)
  - Committee of Safety and Relief at Canandaigua: minute book, list of sufferers and relief records, 1814 (Box-folder 1.9)
  - Manuscripts related to losses on the Niagara Frontier, 1813-1819 (Box-folder 1.10)
  - Letters describing conditions on the Niagara Frontier, 1814 (Box-folder 1.11)
- Commission, Bounty and Pension Papers, 1810-1934, III.
  - Commission, bounties, pensions, 1810-1934 (Box-folder 2.1)
- Reminiscences, Catalogs and Bibliographies, 1899-circa 1953, IV.
  - Läila F. Culbertson, Buffalo in the War of 1812: reminiscence, read before the Graduates' Association, 10 November 1899 (Box-folder 2.2)
  - ALS, Louis Knapp (Buffalo) to Frank H. Severance (Buffalo), re: site of War 1812 mortar found at Massachusetts St. 19 Jan. 1901 (Box-folder 2.3)
  - William Banker, Jr.: The Battle of Queenstown (poem); Prodigal Daughter; &c. (broadside verses ), undated (Box-folder 2.4)
  - Catalogs and bibliographies of War of 1812 materials, circa 1938 (Box-folder 2.5)
  - Catalogs and bibliographies of War of 1812 materials, circa 1938 (Box-folder 2.6)
Search Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the Library's online catalog.
Contributors
Riall, Phineas, Sir, 1775-1850; Camp, John G.; Culbertson, Laila F.; Committee of Safety and Relief at Canandaigua (N.Y.)
Subject Terms
United States--History--War of 1812; United States--History--War of 1812--Reparations; Military Pensions
Genre Terms
Treaties; Military commissions; Pensions; Proclamations; Reminiscences